<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document url="proxy.html">

  &project;
<copyright>
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
   contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
   this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
   The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
   (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
   the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
</copyright>
<properties>
<title>Reverse Proxy HowTo</title>
<author email="rjung@apache.org">Rainer Jung</author>
<date>$Date$</date>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="Introduction"> 
<br/>
<p>The Apache module mod_jk and its ISAPI and NSAPI variants connect
a web server to a backend (typically Tomcat) using the AJP protocol.
The web server receives an HTTP(S) request and the module forwards
the request to the backend. This function is usually called a gateway
or a proxy, in the context of HTTP it is called a reverse proxy.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Typical Problems">
<br/>
<p>A reverse proxy is not totally transparent to the application on
the backend. For instance the host name and port the original client
(e.g. browser) needs to talk to belong to the web server and not to the
backend, so the reverse proxy talks to a different host name and port.
When the application on the backend returns content including
self-referential URLs using its own backend address and port, the
client will usually not be able to use these URLs.
</p>
<p>Another example is the client IP address, which for the web server is the
source IP of the incoming connection, whereas for the backend the
connection always comes from the web server. This can be a problem, when
the client IP is used by the backend application e.g. for security reasons.
</p>
</section>
<section name="AJP as a Solution">
<br/>
<p>Most of these problems are automatically handled by the AJP protocol
and the AJP connectors of the backend. The AJP protocol transports
this communication metadata and the backend connector presents this
metadata whenever the application asks for it using Servlet API methods.
</p>
<p>The following list contains the communication metadata handled by AJP
and the HttpServletRequest API calls which can be used to retrieve them:
<ul>
<li>local name: <code>getLocalName()</code> and <code>getLocalAddr</code>.
This is also equal to <code>getServerName()</code>, unless a <code>Host</code> header
is contained in the request. In this case the server name is taken from that header.
</li>
<li>local port: <code>getLocalPort()</code>
This is also equal to <code>getServerPort()</code>, unless a <code>Host</code> header
is contained in the request. In this case the server port is taken from that header
if it contains an explicit port, or is equal to the default port of the scheme used.
</li>
<li>client address: <code>getRemoteAddr()</code>
</li>
<li>client host: <code>getRemoteHost()</code>
</li>
<li>authentication type: <code>getAuthType()</code>
</li>
<li>remote user: <code>getRemoteUser()</code>,
if <code>tomcatAuthentication="false"</code>
</li>
<li>protocol: <code>getProtocol()</code>
</li>
<li>HTTP method: <code>getMethod()</code>
</li>
<li>URI: <code>getRequestURI()</code>
</li>
<li>HTTPS used: <code>isSecure()</code>, <code>getScheme()</code>
</li>
<li>query string: <code>getQueryString()</code>
</li>
<li>SSL cipher: <code>getAttribute(javax.servlet.request.cipher_suite)</code>
</li>
<li>SSL key size: <code>getAttribute(javax.servlet.request.key_size)</code>.
Can be disabled using <code>JkOptions -ForwardKeySize</code>.
</li>
<li>SSL client certificate: <code>getAttribute(javax.servlet.request.X509Certificate)</code>.
If you want the whole certificate chain, then you need to also set <code>JkOptions ForwardSSLCertChain</code>.
It is likely, that in this case you also need to adjust the maximal AJP packet size
using the worker attribute <a href="../reference/workers.html">max_packet_size</a>.
</li>
<li>SSL session ID: <code>getAttribute(javax.servlet.request.ssl_session)</code>.
This is for Tomcat, it has not yet been standardized.
</li>
</ul>
</p>
</section>
<section name="Fine Tuning">
<br/>
<p>In some situations this is not enough though. Assume there is another
less clever reverse proxy in front of your web server, for instance an
HTTP load balancer or similar device which also serves as an SSL accelerator.
</p>
<p>Then you are sure that all your clients use HTTPS, but your web server doesn't
know about that. All it can see is requests coming from the accelerator using
plain HTTP.
</p>
<p>Another example would be a simple reverse proxy in front of your web server,
so that the client IP address that your web server sees is always the IP address
of this reverse proxy, and not of the original client. Often such reverse proxies
generate an additional HTTP header, like <code>X-Forwareded-for</code> which
contains the original client IP address (or a list of IP addresses, if there are
more cascading reverse proxies in front). It would be nice, if we could use the
content of such a header as the client IP address to pass to the backend.
</p>
<p>So we might need to manipulate some of the data that AJP sends to the backend.
When using mod_jk inside Apache httpd you can use several httpd environment
variables to let mod_jk know, which data it should forward. These environment variables
can be set by the httpd directives SetEnv or SetEnvIf, but also in a very flexible
way using mod_rewrite (since httpd 2.x it can not only test against environment
variables, but also set them).
</p>
<p>The following list contains all environment variables mod_jk checks, before
sending data to the backend:
<ul>
<li>JK_LOCAL_NAME: the local name
</li>
<li>JK_LOCAL_PORT: the local port
</li>
<li>JK_REMOTE_HOST: the client host
</li>
<li>JK_REMOTE_ADDR: the client address
</li>
<li>JK_AUTH_TYPE: the authentication type
</li>
<li>JK_REMOTE_USER: the remote user
</li>
<li>HTTPS: On (case-insensitive) to indicate, that HTTPS is used
</li>
<li>SSL_CIPHER: the SSL cipher
</li>
<li>SSL_CIPHER_USEKEYSIZE: the SSL key size
</li>
<li>SSL_CLIENT_CERT: the SSL client certificate
</li>
<li>SSL_CLIENT_CERT_CHAIN_: prefix of variable names, containing
the client cerificate chain
</li>
<li>SSL_SESSION_ID: the SSL session ID
</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>Remember: in general you don't need to set them. The module retrieves the data automatically
from the web server. Only in case you want to change this data, you can overwrite it by
using these variables.
</p>
<p>Some of these variables might also be used by other web server modules. All
variables whose name does not begin with "JK" are set directly by Apache httpd.
If you want to change the data, but do not want to negatively influence the behaviour
of other modules, you can change the names of all variables mod_jk uses to private ones.
For the details see the <a href="../reference/apache.html">Apache reference</a> page.
</p>
<p>All variables, that are not SSL-related have only been introduced in version 1.2.27.
</p>
<p>Finally there is a shortcut to forward the local IP of the web server as the remote IP.
This can be useful, e.g. when using the Tomcat remote address valve for allowing connections
only from registered Apache web servers. This feature is activated by setting
<code>JkOptions ForwardLocalAddress</code>.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Tomcat AJP Connector Settings">
<br/>
<p>As an alternative to using the environment variables described in the previous section
(which do only exist when using Apache httpd), you can also configure Tomcat to overwrite
some of the communications data forwarded by mod_jk. The AJP connector in Tomcat's <code>server.xml</code>
allows to set the <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-6.0-doc/config/ajp.html#Attributes">following properties</a>:
<ul>
<li>proxyName: server name as returned by <code>getServerName()</code>
</li>
<li>proxyPort: server port as returned by <code>getServerPort()</code>
</li>
<li>scheme: protocol scheme as returned by <code>getScheme()</code>
</li>
<li>secure: set to "true", if you wish <code>isSecure()</code> to return "true".
</li>
</ul>
Remember: in general you don't need to set those. AJP automatically handles all cases
where the web server running mod_jk knows the right data.
</p>
</section>
<section name="URL Handling">
<br/>
<subsection name="URL Rewriting">
<p>Sometimes one want to change path components of the URLs under which an application
is available. Especially if a web application is deployed as some context, say <code>/myapp</code>,
marketing prefers short URLs, so want the application to be directly available under
<code>http://www.mycompany.com/</code>. Although you can deploy the application as the so-called
ROOT context, which will be directly available at "/", admins often prefer not to use
the ROOT context, e.g. because only one application can be the root context (per host).
</p>
<p>The procedure to change the URLs in the reverse proxy is tedious, because often
an application produces self-referential URLs, which then include the path components
which you tried to hide to the outside world. Nevertheless, if you absolutely need to do it,
here are the steps.
</p>
<p>Case A: You need to make the application available at a simple URL, but it is OK, if
users proceed using the more complex URLs, as long as they don't have to type them in.
That's the easy case, and if this suffices to you, you're lucky. Use a simply RedirectMatch
for Apache httpd:
</p>
<source>
RedirectMatch ^/$ http://www.mycompany.com/myapp/
</source>
<p>Your application will then be available under <code>http://www.mycompany.com/</code>,
and each visitor will be immediately redirected to the real URL
<code>http://www.mycompany.com/myapp/</code>
</p>
<p>Case B: You need to hide path components for all requests going to the application.
Here's the recipe for the case, where you want to hide the first path component
<code>/myapp</code>. More complex manipulations are left as an exercise to the reader.
First the solution for the case of Apache httpd:
</p>
<p>1. Use <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/mod/mod_rewrite.html"><code>mod_rewrite</code></a>
to add <code>/myapp</code> to all requests before forwarding to the backend:
</p>
<source>
# Don't forget the PT flag! (pass through)
RewriteRule ^/(.*) http://www.mycompany.com/myapp/$1 [PT]
</source>
<p>2. Use <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/mod/mod_headers.html"><code>mod_headers</code></a>
to rewrite any HTTP redirects your application might return. Such redirects typically contain
the path components you want to hide, because by the HTTP standard, redirects always need to include
the full URL, and your application is not aware of the fact, that your clients talk to it via
some shortened URL. An HTTP redirect is done with a special response header named <code>Location</code>.
We rewrite the Location headers of our responses:
</p>
<source>
# Keep protocol, server and port if present,
# but insert our webapp name before the rest of the URL
Header edit Location ^([^/]*//[^/]*)?/(.*)$ $1/myapp/$2 
</source>
<p>3. Use <code>mod_headers</code> again, to rewrite the paths contained in any cookies,
your application might set. Such cookie paths again might contain
the path components you want to hide.
A cookie is set with the HTTP response header named <code>Set-Cookie</code>.
We rewrite the Set-Cookie headers of our responses:
</p>
<source>
# Fix the cookie path
Header edit Set-Cookie "^(.*; Path=/)(.*)" $1/myapp/$2 
</source>
<p>3. Some applications might contain hard coded absolute links.
In this case check, whether you find a configuration item for your web framework
to configure the base URL. If not, your only chance is to parse all response
content bodies and do search and replace. This is fragile and very resource intensive.
If you really need to do this, you can use
<a href="http://apache.webthing.com/mod_proxy_html/"><code>mod_proxy_html</code></a>,
<a href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/mod/mod_substitute.html"><code>mod_substitute</code></a>
or <a href="http://blogs.sun.com/basant/entry/using_mod_sed_to_filter"><code>mod_sed</code></a>
for this task.
</p>
<p>If you are using Microsoft IIS as a web server, the ISAPI plugin provides a way
of doing the first step with a builtin feature. You define a mapping file for simple prefix
changes like this:
</p>
<source>
# Add a context prefix to all requests ...
/=/myapp/
# ... or change some prefix ...
/oldapp/=/myapp/
</source>
<p>and then put the name of the file in the <code>rewrite_rule_file</code> entry of the registry or your
<code>isapi_redirect.properties</code> file. In you <code>uriworkermap.properties</code> file, you
still need to map the URLs as they are before rewriting!
</p>
<p>More complex rewrites can be done using the same file, but with regular expressions. A leading
tilde sign '<code>~</code>', indicates, that you are using a regular expression:
</p>
<source>
# Use a regular expression rewrite
~/oldapps([0-9]*)/=/newapps$1/
</source>
<p>There is no support for Steps 2 (rewriting redirect responses) or 3 (rewriting cookie paths).
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="URL Encoding">
<p>Some types of problems are triggered by the use of encoded URLs
(see <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Percent-encoding">percent encoding</a>).
For the same location there exist
a lot of different URLs which are equivalent. The reverse proxy needs to inspect the URL in order
to apply its own authentication rules and to decide, to which backend it should send the request
(or whether it should handle it itself). Therefore the request URL first is normalized:
percent encoded characters are decoded, <code>/./</code> is replaced by <code>/</code>,
<code>/XXX/../</code> is replaced by <code>/</code> and similar manipulations of the URL are done.
After that, the web server might apply rewrite rules to further change the URL in less obvious ways.
Finally there is no more way to put the resulting URL in an encoding, which is "similar" to
the one which was used for the original URL.
</p>
<p>
For historical reasons, there have been several alternatives, how mod_jk and the ISAPI
plugin encoded the resulting URL before sending it to the backend. They could be chosen via
<code>JkOptions</code> (Apache httpd) or <code>uri_select</code> (ISAPI). None of those historical
encodings are recommended, because they have either negative functionality implications or
pose a security risk. The default encoding since version 1.2.24 is <code>ForwardURIProxy</code>
(Apache httpd) or <code>proxy</code> (ISAPI) and it is strongly recommended to keep the default
and remove all old explicit settings.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="Request Attributes">
<br/>
<p>
You can also add more attributes to any request you are forwarding when using Apache httpd.
For this use the <code>JkEnvVar</code> directive (for details see the
<a href="../reference/apache.html">Apache reference</a> page). Such request attributes can be
retrieved on the Tomcat side via request.getAttribute(attributeName).
Note that their names will not be listed in request.getAttributeNames()!
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
